Have you ever tried to debug a deployment only to find your
container image is sitting somewhere else?
It might be in someone's local Docker registry or might be
stored in a deprecated Container Registry.
Artifact management can make or break your entire CI/CD pipeline.
That's why Google Cloud's Artifact Registry is
designed to be a single source of truth.
Now let's see how we can use it for better.
First of all, Artifact Registry supports multiple formats.
It supports Docker, Maven, NPM, Python, Go, and generic OCI.
Now for this, I've just created one application that is Docker‑based.
So if I go down to my Open editor, there I have a
sample Flask app that we have created.
Now for this, I'm going to create a repository which is of the format of Docker.
So here it is just saying Hello world.
Now to create the repository,
I go back to my terminal window, and I'm going to type
command like gcloud artifacts repositories.
And then I'm saying create my‑flask‑app‑repo. That is the name of my repository.
Then I'm giving the repository format as Docker and location as asia‑southeast1,
and then any description, whatever you like to give and then say Enter.
This will take a while, and it is going to create our artifact repository.
Not only this,
if you have noticed that we have specifically mentioned the region location.
Google recommends placing artifact repository in the same region
as your GKE cluster or your Cloud Run service,
and it also recommends that create the artifact repository in
the same region where Cloud Build executes.
Actually, this reduces the network latency,
egress cost, build time, and deploy time.
Maybe, let's say for enterprise deployment, you
wanted to do across multiple regions.
In that case, you can create the multiple repos for each and every region,
and then you can use the replication or the promotion pipelines.
If you want to see how this looks like,
you can come down here and search for Artifact Registry.
Now here you can see all the registry which is there in your account.
So here you can see that all the registry which is there in my account,
what I can do is I can go down to my specific repository.
I can specifically assign the IAM roles,
which sometimes is very important based on the
specific operation someone wanted to do.
So I can select my application and say Show Info panel. And here I
can add these specific roles and permission.
I can say Add principal, and for a specific set of users or a group,
I can assign the roles.
Maybe I'm interested in assigning the Artifact Reader Role,
or maybe I'm interested in assigning the writer permission for,
let's say, Cloud Build, or maybe read permission for Cloud Deploy.
So according to the need,
we can assign the roles and permission for this specific registry.
Enterprises use the Artifact Registry for a couple of more reasons.
One of them is a vulnerability scanning.
Google automatically runs and scans the vulnerabilities on pushed images.
You can enforce the policies to block the deployments when critical
CVs found fail builds if base images are outdated.
Another important best practice is to have your immutable tagging.
You never overwrite the tags like prod or let us use the commit SHAs
instead and then promote the version's metadata,
not re‑tags.
By default, the Artifact Registry is private, which is exactly what you want.
With the binary authorization,
teams can sign container images before they deploy.
This prevents tampered images, unapproved builds, unauthorized pushes.
Specifically, many finance and healthcare organizations require this.
Not only this, over a period of time,
the artifacts build up hundreds of the versions,
old images, unused tags,
all taking up this space and money. Artifact Registry
supports the cleanup policy that you can set.
For example, you can go back to your repository.
When you go inside your repository and say Edit repository,
in your repository here itself, you can add the cleanup policy.
And when you set up a cleanup policy,
you can give a name and you can decide the basis on
which you want to do cleanup.
Maybe you wanted to do the conditional delete,
saying that if a specific image is older then this is specific,
then you can remove it.
Or maybe you wanted to keep only some specific number of recent version.
Say, I don't want it to have more than 50 images,
so you can keep that specific number of accounts.
So this is how you can even set up your cleanup policy.
This is going to be extremely useful for the teams doing the frequent releases.
So that's how you can configure the Artifact Registry for a secure,
scalable CI/CD workflow and integration with the Cloud Build and Cloud Deploy.